Finding Aid for Karl Frank Lagler papers, 1941-1970
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Karl Frank Lagler papers 1941-1970, 1945-1960
Lagler Karl Frank, 1912-
2.5 linear feet
851617 Aa 2
Professor of fisheries and zoology at University of Michigan. Correspondence files detailing his professional career and his interests in conservation, ichthyology, and fishery research and development.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was received in multiple accessions between March 1973 and November 1990 (donor no. 4001 ).
Periodic additions to the records are not expected.
The collection is open to research.
Karl Frank Lagler was born November 15, 1912 in Rochester, New York, the son of Leo and Rosalie (Nicolet) Lagler. He received a B.A. in biology from the University of Rochester in 1934 and a M.S. in vertebrate zoology and fisheries from Cornell in 1936. Lagler joined the faculty of the University of Michigan's School of Natural Resources in 1939 and completed his Ph.D. in zoology and fisheries here in 1940. In 1950, Lagler was instrumental in the establishment of the Department of Fisheries within the School of Natural Resources and served as chairman of the department until 1965. In addition to being named the Justin V. Leonard Distinguished Professor of Natural Resources in 1977, Lagler was awarded the title of professor emeritus (1984) following his retirement in 1983.
Lagler achieved both national and international recognition as an expert on fisheries, conservation, and the fishes of the Great Lakes Region. Lagler was active in numerous professional societies, elected to fellowship in six national and international scientific associations, and served as president for both the American Institute of Fishery Research Biologists and the International Academy of Fishery Scientists in the 1960s. Lagler traveled widely as a consultant for many governmental and private agencies, both domestic and foreign, including the United Nation's Food and Agriculture Organization.
An energetic and prolific scholar, Lagler authored or co-authored more than one hundred-thirty technical and popular articles, papers, and books. In 1950, Lagler taught the first university telecourse, and went on to complete more than one hundred educational television programs, as well as a weekly radio show on conservation from 1963 to 1972. Tapes of several Lagler television programs, as well as scripts, study guides, and one tape of the university telecourse, are held by the Bentley Historical Library as part of the Michigan Media Collection.
Karl Frank Lagler died August 25, 1985.
The original order of the Karl Frank Lagler papers has been maintained and comprises one alphabetically arranged series of topical files.
The bulk of the documents within the files consist of correspondence between Lagler and other fishery biologists throughout the world. Also included, however, are files containing reports and minutes of meetings from a number of scientific and sporting associations in which Lagler was active. Lagler's research interests are well represented in the several groups of files dedicated to his various research projects. His work with salmon in Alaska as a consultant for the U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service in the summer of 1958 is particularly well documented. Research project files are alphabetized by geographic place name (i.e., Fleming Creek; Golden Lake; Port Walter, Alaska). In addition to background materials, notes, and final reports on the research project, many of these files contain a substantial amount of raw data on several Michigan lakes and ponds. Together, Lagler's correspondence with his colleagues, the materials he collected concerning his activities with a variety of organizations, and his own research materials chronicle the development of fishery conservation as a profession and as a science in the 1940s and 1950s.
The collection contains a fair amount of correspondence concerning several of Lagler's publications, but not as much as might be expected from such a prolific scholar. Although some course and University materials are included in the collection, there is little documentation of Lagler's administrative work as Chair of the Department of Fisheries from 1950 to 1965. Likewise, there is little documentation of Lagler's activities as a consultant for numerous foreign governments as well as for the United Nations.
Lagler filed his correspondence either by the last name of the correspondent or by subject. Therefore, researchers should search for materials on specific topics by both correspondent and subject.
Subjects:
Conservation of natural resources--Michigan.; Fishes--Michigan.; Lagler, Karl F. (Karl Frank), 1912-1985; Natural resources--Michigan.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Fisheries.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Zoology.; University of Michigan--Faculty.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Alaska.; Fish hatcheries.; Lagler, Karl F. (Karl Frank), 1912-1985; Port Walter (Alaska); University of Michigan--Faculty.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Topical Files
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
  - A 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - Alaska 1947-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science 1957-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Association of University Professors 1958-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Fisheries Society 1948-1962 (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Biological Sciences 1949-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Institute of Fishery Research Biologists 1959-1970, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - American Society of Ichthyologists and Herpetologists 1947-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Society of Limnology and Oceanography 1951-1959 (Box 1)
  - American Wildlife Institute 1937-1940 (Box 1)
  - Association of Great Lakes Outdoor Writers 1963-1965 (Box 1)
  - B 1941-1963 (Box 1)
  - C 1947-1959 (Box 1)
  - Committee on College Problems (U of M) 1945-1950 (Box 1)
  - "Conservation of Fishery Resources," Article 1958 (Box 1)
  - Continental Fisheries, Book, Vibert and Lagler, 1959 (Box 1)
  - D 1949-1961 (Box 1)
  - Department of Zoology (U of M) 1947-1948 (Box 1)
  - E-F 1947-1958 (Box 1)
  - Ecologists Union 1947-1949 (Box 1)
  - "Education for Professional Careers in Fisheries," Article, Lagler and Suvatti 1965 (Box 1)
  - Exploratory Fishing and Gear Research Project 1967, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - "Fish Ecology" (Zoology 623)-Course Materials circa 1959-1960 (Box 1)
  - Fish Taggers Association 1953-1957 (Box 1)
  - Fleming Creek Research Project-Survey Data and Map 1940-1961 (Box 1)
  - Food and Agriculture Organization (United Nations) 1954-1959 (Box 1)
  - Food-chain Radioactivity Transfer Project (Lake Erie) 1960-1961 (Box 1)
  - G 1947-1959 (Box 1)
  - Golden Lake Research Project-Materials 1951-1952, 3 folders (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Fisheries Commission 1956-1958 (Box 1)
  - Great Lakes Research Institute (U of M) 1945-1960 (Box 2)
  - H 1947-1959 (Box 2)
  - I-J 1952-1959 (Box 2)
  - Institute for Fisheries Research 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - K 1947-1956 (Box 2)
  - Kellogg Gull Lake Biological Station-Summer Courses 1959 (Box 2)
  - L 1947-1951 (Box 2)
  - Laboratory of Vertebrate Zoology (U of M) 1947-1949 (Box 2)
  - Life in Flowing Waters, Book, Bardach and Lagler, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Loch Alpine Ponds Research Project-Materials 1948-1952, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - M 1956-1959 (Box 2)
  - Midwest Wildlife Conference 1948, 1954, 1956 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous 1954-1963 (Box 2)
  - Mohawk Business Machines Corporation 1955-1956 (Box 2)
  - N-O 1951-1958 (Box 2)
  - P-Q 1944-1958 (Box 2)
  - Pasinski's Pond (Livingston County, Michigan) Research Project in Sterility of Hybrid Sunfish 1951-1952 (Box 2)
  - Pleasant Lakes Club (Michigan) 1948-1952 (Box 2)
  - Porcupine Mountain (Michigan) Research Project, Materials and Photographs, 1948-1949 (Box 2)
  - Port Walter, Alaska Research Project
    - Correspondence 1958-1960 (Box 2)
    - Materials 1958 (Box 2)
    - "Salmon Survival Investigations," Field Report 1958 (Box 2)
    - "Alaskan Commercial Fisheries," Field Report 1958 (Box 2)
    - "Dolly Varden," Articles, Lagler and Wright 1960-1961 (Box 2)
    - Field Notes and Maps 1958 (Box 2)
    - Slide Presentation Scripts 1958-1959 (Box 2)
    - Photographs, 1958 (Box 2)
  - Possible Research Projects 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - "Professionalism in Fish Biology," Lagler Survey and Responses 1953, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Progressive Fish Culturist, Articles, 1947-1949 (Box 2)
  - Publications, Miscellaneous 1947-1948 (Box 2)
  - R 1945-1957 (Box 2)
  - Research Club (U of M) 1956 (Box 2)
  - Research Grants-Proposals and Reports 1945-1960 (Box 2)
  - S 1948-1958 (Box 2)
  - Sabbatical Leave 1957-1958 (Box 2)
  - Saylor Estate Caribou Lake Research Project-Materials 1953 (Box 2)
  - Sport Fishing Institute 1949-1959 (Box 3)
  - Statistical Research Laboratory (U of M) 1956 (Box 3)
  - T 1955-1958 (Box 3)
  - Tehuantepec (Mexico)-Project Proposal 1957 (Box 3)
  - Television Programs 1949-1956 (Box 3)
  - Trout Unlimited 1959-1965 (Box 3)
  - U-Z 1949-1958 (Box 3)
  - Underwater Television 1954 (Box 3)
  - "U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service-Division of Fishery Biology," Report 1948 (Box 3)
  - Wildlife Management Institute 1947-1948 (Box 3)
  - Wildlife Society 1951-1959 (Box 3)
  - Wisconsin Trout Fishermen's Association 1959 (Box 3)